[Music]
so so where were we uh in
the last class we looking at
uh looking at bman I mean mdps and looking here
the mman equation right so
the mdps are defined by S
A right so this is what we use for
defining an mdp correct and what
was the bman equation let's stick with the
bman equation for v for the Simplicity sake
tell me tell me that
uh
okay expectation of
okay and likewise we had
another optimality equation
right so we have the optimality
equation so one thing which I
want you to note about the optimality
equation is that we making an assumption
that so the optimal policy would have a same
Max here right right so that's fine correct
right another assumption that he
will make as we go along uh trying
to solve the mdp is that uh the optimal policy is
deterministic right so and we'll
also use this following notation
instead of saying Pi of a given
s I'll use the notation Pi of
yes so Pi of s is essentially a single action
a that we will always do whenever we come to
status right so Pi of a given is a probability
distribution right this is essentially saying that
if my Pi is such that it is one for one action
and zero for all the rest for every state right
then I can represent it as just Pi s where Pi
will return the action for which the probability
is one okay so this is a deterministic policy so
this is a notation that we'll use so this denotes
a right and later on we'll see that we'll make an
assumption that the deterministic policy I mean
the optimal policy is deterministic right um in
fact more uh correctly we'll assume that if the
mdp has an optimal policy then there exists
a deterministic optimal policy right there
could be multiple stochastic optimal policies but
that that will exist at least one deterministic
optimal policy so that's assumption that we'll
make okay so later so in fact uh I'll see if I
can actually develop all the missionary required
to prove that uh but uh we don't have to go do
that right so uh we'll see if I don't get to that
then please take it on faith um okay so a couple
of things so now I'm going to talk about uh so
the existence and the uniqueness of solutions
for these uh sets of equations right we going
to talk about the existence and uniqueness of
solutions for the set of equations so for us
to get into that we need a little bit of uh
analysis right so we need to know a little bit of
fundas from functional analysis uh uh and so I'll
I'm going to keep it very very light okay I'm not
don't worry I'm not going to do anything very uh
very deep in this but for that people have to
recall all their things about Vector spaces
and so on so forth people remember Vector
spaces right so Vector spaces you have
a set of elements that are closed under
addition and scalar multiplication right
right right so we are going to consider at some
point uh um so I'll come to that so one way of
thinking about uh the value functions right
in a finite mdp you can think about it in a
non discrete State space also but for the for
Simplicity sake let's assume that uh what I'm
going to talk about now is only about finite
mdps so what are finite mdps these are mdps
where s is finite right and a is finite both
s and a are finite and we already know that
the expectation should be bounded right so
these are the three conditions that we need
when we say finite mdp then s is finite a is
finite and this expectation is bounded okay
so if you think of a finite mdp I can think
of my value function as a vector in a size
of s dimensional Vector space right so I can
think of it as a vector which has s components
[Music]
okay in
fact so it's a it's a space on
which I can define a notion of
a norm right Norm is something like a size of
the you can think of it roughly as equalent to
being size of the vector right I can define
a norm on this Vector space right but I'm
interested in using a specific kind of Norm on
this space which we'll call the max Norm right
so people know Norms okay so
you can think of it as some
kind of a measure of size right
uh so I just put this down here
okay so if and only if x is z n x is z right
and alpha x is Alpha where Alpha is a scalar
is Alpha time Norm of x and this is the
triangle inequality okay great we have
this no I'm just seeing what notations I
should introduce for you okay so that's
fine so people know know all about Vector
spaces okay so in Vector space where you
have a norm defined on the vectors
is called a normed vector space okay
so all of you know that great so now I
want to talk about something called a
complete normed Vector space we all know about
what a nored vector spaces so
when do you say it is complete
okay so for that we need to
understand something called a
what is
it not C inequality we need to understand
what's called a quy quy sequence okay
so a sequence of course is something like
this okay okay right so what do kosi
sequence it says that okay for any
real Epsilon that you give me I can find
some point in the sequence okay Beyond
which if I pick any two elements
they are within Epsilon of each
other essentially says for any Epsilon you
give me right so what does this mean so the
sequence should be say that the successive
elements are coming closer closer and closer
to each other correct does it make sense it's
a sequence in which the successive elements
are coming closer and closer to each other so
if every CI sequence in a norm Vector space
converges to a point in the vector space right
then you call the vector space as a complete space
so X1 and X2 the distance between X1 and X2 will
be greater than X2 and X3 X1 is a constant yeah
yes so X1 and X2 the distance will be greater
than X2 and X3 possibly it should can you show
that from the definition of a c sequence
uh the C sequence just says the successive
difference are getting smaller and smaller and
smaller doesn't necessarily say there's a limit
right doesn't necessarily say there is a limit it
just says become smaller and smaller and smaller
and smaller smaller so you could have a limit
right that's outside the space that you are
considering right so if you want to
look at examples of CI sequences that
are not Cent go look at wik Wikipedia
right so there are enough material out
there that talk about all of these
things right so you could have them
becomes smaller and smaller and smaller
right but the point to which they converge
might be a point which doesn't belong
to the the space that you originally are
defining right so these kinds of uh things
would happen uh because when we're dealing
with infinitely long sequences all kinds of
crazy things happen Okay uh yeah I should have
noted down one such example anyone can recall an
example of the top of their head non-convergent Cy
sequences something with like
1 by n and it converges to zero
but then you can define a space which excludes
zero right can you can you define
a vector space that exclude
zero h no then they have to come
up with some other example say
something that converges to some other value
1 - 1 1 - 1 by x 1 - 1 - 1 byx will converge
to one now Define a space that excludes one
then right so but that people get the
idea right so CI sequences might not be
convergent in the in the domain that you are
operating in right so the if every CI sequence
okay
good so I think that's all we need from
that okay so I'm going to introduce
a few more Vector notation so that uh
we can translate all these bman equations
into into some uh nice underlying Vector
space and then show some results there
okay uh so we already have v as a vector
so I'm going to Define r Pi of s
essentially I'm saying that what
is the reward I'll get in state yes
for following policy Pi what is expected
reward in state test for following policy
Pi it makes life a little simple you can
see some of this thing here I am kind of
compressing and writing it as a single
Vector okay essentially the first term
here right I have compressed
it and I'm writing it as RPS
okay which is the reward I expect to get
starting in state s and following policy
Pi it's like the immediate One Step
reward right it's not it's not the
expected reward so return we need the
VP gamma VP right just the one step
reward that I'll get starting from his
following five so likewise I'm going to
write so this gives me the the one step
transition probability under policy pi
right I fixed policy PI right so this will give me
the one step transition probability under policy
Pi so what is the probability I'll end up in
state J if I start from State s and take one
action according to policy Pi there could be
many ways in which I can get to State J from
State s right okay good so these are the two
things that we needed and soest as an asite
uh if I'm using a deterministic thing this
becomes a little easier so this will essentially
be right so deterministic policy so at
some points it makes it easier for us
to explicitly consider deterministic
policies so I'm just writing out the
notation here so whenever I want to use
deterministic policies I might actually
switch to this notation the summation over a
disappears right so likewise here this will be
just because there only one action I'll take
under policy PI right therefore the probability
of going to J from s is a probability of
going to J from s under that action Pi of
s okay it's just a notational convenience okay
so don't don't work work yourself too much about
it right so one thing to not is this RP is
a s dimensional Vector again so R Pi sorry
R Pi is s dimensional vector and P Pi is a s cross
s dimensional Matrix okay and it's also a special
kind of matrix it's a stochastic Matrix so what's
a stochastic Matrix columns add up to rows add up
to one and anything else greater than all the
Val areer than Z on negative greater than equal
to Z okay so all the all the rows are greater than
equal to zero essentially each row you can think
of it as a discrete probability distribution
right they all the the entries in a row sum
up to one and they all have to be non- negative
so basically they lie between zero and one then
so the normal assumption we going to make is that
gamma lies between zero included and one okay this
assumption we'll make and if you think about
it that one step return right I can write it as
all I'll come to that in a minute
right so what do you think this
is so if you think of an mdp right where I'm
making one decision right so that decision
is going to cost me to make a transition to some
state right and starting from some some state some
s okay I'm making a decision it's going to cause
a transition to a state J right there will be a
reward along the way and I also have a terminal
cost or a terminal reward for landing in J okay
that terminal reward is given by the function V so
if you think of it this way so my entire problem
consists of taking only one step right I pick a
step I I I mean I take an action I perform it I I
an action I perform the action I'm going to make
one transition and that's it I'll end right and
what will happen is for that one transition
I'll get some reward right and for ending
in that particular State J I'm going to get some
payoff for ending in j right and that payoff let
us say is given by V then this is the total reward
I'm going to get right so R is the reward for the
one transition and V is the final cost right
and where I'm going to land up is determined
by P Pi okay you can think of it as a one-step
transition function where the terminal cost is
given by V so what we really want to do is instead
of assuming that there is some arbitrary function
V that is giving us this terminal cost we want
to find a function V PI right which in some sense
substitutes for the terminal cost of following
policy PI right right so we want a v Pi that
satisfies this
equation okay so you can see why V Pi is a
terminal cost right so it's like what is V
Pi it's a value I'm going to get expected return
I'm going to get starting from the next state and
following I mean starting from that state and
following policy F right so one way of thinking
about it is my decision problem ended with making
one decision right I made the choice according to
Pi I stopped there and whatever the future
reward is I'm going to consider that as one
value and then add it to my function so that's VP
so I'm thinking thinking treating VP as a terminal
cost for a one step decision problem right and
then what I really want this VP to satisfy it
should be the total cost right of starting from
here so this is essentially the equation that I
want to solve for VP okay so I'll come to V Star
later this is the equation I want to solve for V
PI right so people are all on board with this
right right so you can substitute that for R
pi and this for p pi and you write it out you
see that it's essentially this expression right
I could have started from this expression
and simplified it there but I wanted you
to look at the other way of uh interpreting
this expression that is why I started with
this terminal cost interpretation okay so if the
terminal cost interet ation doesn't appeal to you
you can do Algebra start from this expression
which which I hopefully convinced you in the
last class is correct right simplify it you'll
get that expression okay great so this implies
that okay
very simple asbra just took this to other
side that took multiplied by the inverse
on both sides I get this okay so what
can you say about this Matrix is it
invertible remember determinants uh anyway fine
so well you know what the I values of I are
all ones right and what about P
piastic stochastic so the largest value for a
stochastic Matrix is one okay so the largest
value for a stochastic Matrix is one and
I multiplied gamma so the largest I value
is going to be less than one so the whole
Matrix that cannot have a zero again value
therefore this thing will be invertible
right and therefore that there exists a
unique solution for VP can you explain the
reasoning one what's that so for stochastic
matrices right the igen values the largest igen
value for a stochastic Matrix is one okay this
is why I said this is particularly mentioned
that this thing is a stochastic Matrix right
because the rows all sum to one you can show
with little bit of work that the largest I
value for stochastic Matrix is one okay so so
I'm multiplying it by gamma Which is less than
one right so this whole thing is going to be
going to have an igen value largest igen value
Which is less than one right and the igen
values for I are all one right so if you
take the difference Matrix and try to find the
igen values for those right it cannot have an
igen value of zero right as long as a matrix
does not have an igen value of zero it is
invertible this is basic
linear algebra properties right
uh right so yeah so it's invertible therefore
this is unique there's a unique solution to this
and we all set right so this is sometimes known
as the green equation uh but not always because
there's something else also called The Greens
equation I don't want to write it down there
right so this is one way of showing that VP is
unique right rank must be equal to dimension
for a sorry rank must be equal to dimension for a
unique solution if it's in must diens for it to be
in okay fine this is one way of convincing
people that this works right so another way
of convincing people is to look at the whole
dynamics of what happens right in that equation
right so think about something like this
right I start with some arbitrary function
for V Pi I start with an arbitrary guess for
VP okay so I plug this in here right and I'm
going to solve this equation not solve
I'm just going to run this computation
so I'm going to get another expression for I
mean another value for V PI right let's start
with some arbitrary guess let us call it V
not okay I'll compute this I'll get say V1
right and then I'll go back and plug V1 back
into this expression okay I'll compute this
I'll get V2 right I keep doing this iteratively
right I'm going to claim that this will converge
to V PI right I'm going to make several
claims I'm going to I mean I made several
claims in that statement first claim was it's
going to converge second claim was third claim
is it's Unique right so we already know it's
Unique from this expression this thing this
thing we know it's Unique but I can also try to
show it in a different way right so I'm going to
show that it's going to converge right and it'll
converge to V pi and that V Pi is unique right
so the reason I'm going to do it this way is it
makes it easier for us to handle the optimality
equation as well later right so if I if I show
you how to do this in the VP case it makes it
easier for us to handle the optimality equation
later okay great so so people have heard me before
know that I'm going dead slow today I would have
normally finished everything I wanted to do by
now but uh I'll probably go to a second class
okay because I wanted to make sure that people
get what's what I'm saying right uh so let's
see so if you have any questions or anything
uh are you completely lost how many of you
are completely lost that's basic basic linear
algebra basic linear algebra so go do do
me a favor go Google up relationship of
igen values to invertibility of matrices
okay you probably get a stack Overflow
hit okay oh no no stack stack exchange
hit stack exchange hit yeah no no that's
a stat exchange right stat exch yeah you'll
probably get a stat exchange hit on this yeah
uh anyway so that's that's very basic stuff
right so so you remember about determinants
and products of again values being equal
to determinant right so a matrix is not
invertible only if the determinant is zero
right and if no I value is zero then the
determinant cannot be zero therefore the
Matrix will be invertible okay okay that
convince you maybe a bit more okay anyway
fine so go go look up so I'm not going to
do basic linear algebra now okay so let's now
take you kicking and screaming into something
more I I need to erase this
part which part can I erase
okay so I'll probably end up erasing this
part so everyone has copied down what this
R pi and P Pi are right so everyone has
it in their notebook so I can erase this
because I'm going to use it but I want
that expression also to stay I don't
want to erase that so everyone has this
great so I'm going to erase it [Applause]